so there's a suter uh something called
20.4 called pots of food and that's
because if someone were to give away a
hundred pots of food as a charity in the
morning 100 pots of food is a charity at
noon and a hundred pots of food is a
church in the evening and if someone
else were to develop a mind of
friendliness even for a time
even for a time
it takes to pull a cow's other either in
the morning at noon or in the evening
this would be more fruitful than the
former therefore because you should train
therefore because you should train
yourself thus we will develop and
cultivate the liberation of mind by
friendliness make it a vehicle make it a
basis stabilize it exercise ourselves in
it and fully perfect it
thus you should train yourselves
so this refers to the uh
the practice of meta or how it's often
translated as loving kindness but
but
it's really about about the mind of
friendliness that is sustained regardless of the
that is sustained regardless of the
circumstances
so the first thing that a person will
realize is that
yeah you can
you can evoke an attitude of
friendliness towards everyone but um it
doesn't last
or it lasts only relatively
speaking sooner or later it's just it will it
sooner or later it's just it will it
will kind of drift into that uh abstract
thinking of you keep repeating to
yourself friendliness and friendliness
but practically speaking your mind is
very much not friendly so how do you
deal with that how do you
how do you address that well the reason
why the mind doesn't listen to you
is because as the buddha said it's not
pliable so it hasn't been uh tamed
enough um it hasn't been brought
um it hasn't been brought
into your control
which means your sense restraint
guarding of the sense doors and your
watchfulness has not been sufficiently developed
has not been sufficiently developed
so so that's that's why
even if you were to understand
um how to cultivate the attitude even if
you could quickly evoke
an attitude of friendliness let's say
like that
it will not
get established in your mind because the
mind is still not not taint not tamed to
the extent necessary
for those phenomena to take root to take
place and then to to stay enduring there
so um
so that's why we often mention you know
regardless whether it's the matter
practice or china practice or
whichever other forms of samadhi you
want to practice that all has to come
after your mind has been tamed and
brought into um
well into like a like
a good degree of your control so in
other words that the mind needs to start
to listen to you so whereby then when
you think
the thoughts of friendliness the mind
will become the mind of friendliness
now you can think the thoughts of
friendliness but it's just
you know trying to layer over over a
very over over a mind that is very
unfriendly or certainly
even if you if you if you make all the
effort and constantly sort of um
dwell on thoughts of friendliness and
thoughts of kindness
the mind kind of becomes indifferent
towards it
and the reason for that is
uh
the mind has not been sufficiently
developed on its own has not been
sufficiently tamed
which means you are still
more influenced by your mind and your
mind is influenced by you and that's the
problem and that's why all these
contemplations that would encourages
monks to do
pretty much apply to people that have
already contained their mind in that
right way
the mind and friendliness say
you say somebody has tamed their minds
officially enough
they don't need
they wouldn't need many specific
instructions on how to do how to do meta
and uh because again just the thought of
friendliness for a well-trained mind
mind that has been drained in
mind that obeys you and listens to you
mind it doesn't drift into sensuality
you know at a in a split second
it doesn't fall into a will in a split
second uh all you need to do then is just
uh all you need to do then is just
remember a a friendly attitude
regardless of the the person regardless
of the specific
um
man or a woman you were friendly to
and just
just take the phenomenon of friendliness
and um
and dwell on it that's it and the mind
will then direct or rather the mind will
then follow that direction
and it will be friendly
towards anything and anyone
even people that are hostile that
doesn't mean that you would not perceive
the hostility or
bad behavior or foolish people around
but he will not
have ill built towards them because
the the direction of ill will is
directly opposite of the direction of
friendliness and now given that the mind that listens
and now given that the mind that listens
to you has already traveled far enough
in the direction of friendliness
uh even when it faces something that's
not really
nice uh a person or something like that
uh a person or something like that
um it will take a lot more effort
to you know go back now from the
direction of friendliness into the
direction of will and then have the ill
will developed then to just stay there
and not change its framework of
friendliness um regardless of the of the behavior of
um regardless of the of the behavior of
that person
so that's the that's how you truly
practice matter and that's what would
have said yeah it will lead to complete
liberation of the mind if you sustain it
the the
the presence of that attitude the
friendliness is completely as i said incompatible
is completely as i said incompatible
with the attitude of
ill will attitude of craving
acting out of your desires so if
friendliness is sustained
passion will diminish
and you can again
it's not like you don't you shouldn't be
trying to practice this until you
develop your mind
um so that mind obeys you and listens to
you and so on but you you do need to be
aware that there is a certain order of
things how you develop them so
you can
try and keep making effort to practice
matter but if you're not sustaining it if the
but if you're not sustaining it if the
mind is not quite you know
as friendly as it should be and if that
framework of friendliness is not present
throughout the day
it's not because matt is wrong or
that meditation is not for you or
something no it's because the mind has
not been tamed enough
so it's not mutually exclusive so it's
not like i will not do meta until i tame
my mind no you can you can keep taming
your mind
uh and keep practicing meta which will
kind of at the same time
serve as a criteria of how tamed your
mind is
because if you're not trying to to to to
direct your mind in like for example in
this example in the direction of
friendliness uh well you will not see how much it
uh well you will not see how much it
disobeys you
and that's that's the point so you you
do try to practice this and then see if
the mind disobeys you which means okay
so
review start things from the beginning
so is your is your virtue you know up to
the up to the task has it been purified
up to the task has it been purified
enough are you seeing the danger in the
slightest fault are your precepts intact
are you watchful generally of your
intentions you know and whereby you know
you're choosing things out of desire
boredom or real will
uh and if so if you recognize that their
blemishes their heart will say okay you
correctly there in that regard
and then keep
trying to develop the attitude of
friendliness because if that uh
because if that uh
taming of the mind is is is is done or
when it is done properly
the um the attitude of friendliness will
be much easier to establish and it will
last much longer on its own
so so you can use that
like you can use the
attempts at trying to to practice uh
friendliness correctly
you can use that pretty much as a as a
kind of a measure of how
much more your mind needs to be tamed
and then
eventually when there is no effort
required for you to sustain the attitude
of friendliness
uh regardless as i said of the
circumstances you know okay so the mind
now is quite pliable and and it listens
to me and then you can choose other ways
of developing your mind you could start
pondering on
on the first jhana or or any other types
of composure
composure
and now the mind will will be much more
obedient and those all those subtle
phenomenas of uh
of these um of these practices that
would result in in complete liberation
mine would become much more apparent
much more palpable let's put it that way
so and you can also just use the the
similar you can you can extrapolate this
principle and apply it to to anything
you read in the sutures so if things are
not understood or if they seem too
abstract or too sort of far-fetched
um
that's because the mind is not quite on
the level
where you can understand those things so
the mind has not been tamed enough has
not been withdrawn from centrality
enough has not been acting has not been
abstaining from acting out of desire
long enough and that's why these things
are just abstract that's just
these distant ideas that you don't even
see any basis for application in this
experience here and now but all that can
change if the mind
taming is is gradually developed and sustained
is is gradually developed and sustained
and and that's the that's kind of the
necessary order of things